<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gatsby.Js on Kalin Chernev</title>
    <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/tags/gatsby.js/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gatsby.Js on Kalin Chernev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - 2017</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://kalinchernev.github.io/tags/gatsby.js/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Admin UI for Gatsby static site generator</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/admin-ui-gatsby-static-site-generator/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2017 23:33:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/admin-ui-gatsby-static-site-generator/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I was looking into &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gatsbyjs.org/&#34;&gt;Gatsby.js&lt;/a&gt; as a generator for a blog site. As many others, I one of the first steps into using the system as other popular CMS solutions, I started to look around for an online back-end UI for the content creation part. I found this list of &lt;a href=&#34;https://headlesscms.org/&#34;&gt;headless CMS options&lt;/a&gt; and since &lt;a href=&#34;forestry.io&#34;&gt;forestry&lt;/a&gt; (the service I use for my blog) does not support Gatsby, I decided to try &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlifycms.org/&#34;&gt;NetlifyCMS&lt;/a&gt;. This tutorial will be about it :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going into details on the separate services and software packages, their advantages and super features. Rather, I will keep the tutorial concise on how to integrate the systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like more background about the JAM stack, you can see previous mentions &lt;a href=&#34;https://kalinchernev.github.io/march-digest-2017/#jam-stack&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://kalinchernev.github.io/releasing-new-blog/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;start&#34;&gt;Start&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the tutorial, assume I&amp;rsquo;m speaking about &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Vagr9K/gatsby-advanced-starter&#34;&gt;gatsby advanced starterkit&lt;/a&gt; although same principles apply to which-ever starterkit or gatsby setup. The important part is to have markdown as data source, as well as well-defined front-matter parsed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/gatsbyjs/gatsby/tree/master/packages/gatsby-transformer-remark&#34;&gt;gatsby-transformer-remark&lt;/a&gt; and exposed to a GraphQL API within the Gatsby. In short, make sure you have markdown files so that the information you write is &amp;ldquo;understood&amp;rdquo; by NetlifyCMS and Gatsby, and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;netlifycms&#34;&gt;NetlifyCMS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an open source decoupled back-end built on React, which &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlifycms.org/docs/intro/&#34;&gt;integrates with Github API&lt;/a&gt;. I personally like this idea, because publishing work-flows actually translate to steps developers already take on code repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use this admin UI application easily, you can &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/netlify/netlify-cms/blob/master/docs/quick-start.md&#34;&gt;integrate it with the Netlify service&lt;/a&gt; which will watch for changes in your github repository and do the necessary builds, previews and deploys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make Gatsby work with this tutorial, you will need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;make a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gatsbyjs.org/docs/building-with-components/#page-components&#34;&gt;page component&lt;/a&gt; for the admin page, this should include the scripts loading the NetlifyCMS app&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;include the &lt;code&gt;config.yml&lt;/code&gt; file in &lt;code&gt;static&lt;/code&gt; folder of Gatsby, as it does not need optimization by webpack&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have configured Netlify service to take your master branch and execute &lt;code&gt;npm run build&lt;/code&gt; on new deployments, a new push will already give you access to the admin UI app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gatsby&#34;&gt;Gatsby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This side might seem a bit more complex compared to copy-paste and rework to a small React component, but it&amp;rsquo;s actually a simple process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;move all markdown files into 1 folder, you need a flat structure, otherwise NetlifyCMS won&amp;rsquo;t be able to list the existing content in the dashboard&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;configure the &lt;code&gt;SiteConfig.js&lt;/code&gt; ​to point to this folder containing the files&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;configure also, by the way, configure also the &lt;code&gt;config.yml&lt;/code&gt; of Netlify to be the same target&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check if all works, and if yes, make another deployment to the your repository. I personally removed all the unnecessary content manually and had to flush the cache of the last deploy in the console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-result&#34;&gt;The result&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a modern tool-chain of React, GraphQL, webpack, and similar, called Gatsby, and you have a working administration UI to manage your content when you&amp;rsquo;re lazy to open your editor ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kalinchernev/kalinchernev.github.io/blob/blog/static/videos/netlify-cms-gatsby.mp4&#34;&gt;video of the process&lt;/a&gt; from making a draft which is a pull request, opening a preview and then publishing the change which gets automatically deployed on the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://kalinchernev.github.io/uploads/2017/08/16/Aug%2017%202017%2012-41%20AM.mp4&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>