<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kalin Chernev</title>
    <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Kalin Chernev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - 2017</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2017 15:33:06 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://kalinchernev.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2017 15:33:06 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, my name is Kalin Chernev, and this website is probably my 5th place to blog, I stopped counting.
My track of experience is filled with projects on Drupal and sometimes a bit of WordPress,
but this time there&amp;rsquo;s no CMS behind this website. This website/blog is hosted on github pages for 2 main reasons: &lt;strong&gt;be close to code&lt;/strong&gt; from github, and &lt;strong&gt;keep things simple&lt;/strong&gt; hosting only HTML, CSS and JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I&amp;rsquo;m working mostly with JavaScript in various forms. That&amp;rsquo;s why you will encounter the notes I&amp;rsquo;m taking
in this blog on my way of understanding concepts, trying frameworks, experimenting with libraries
and all sorts of tools solving problems with JavaScript. It&amp;rsquo;s just amazing how this language got so
versatile to solve so many types of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web has evolved so much in recent years, and the speed of evolution is accelerating greatly.
We solve more complex problems, which lead to even more sophisticated problems to solve.
Thus, this blog keeps things simple - it&amp;rsquo;s plain good old HTML, CSS and JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe in experimentation and open source contribution as a way to learn and keep up
with the accelerated pace of change in Web. That&amp;rsquo;s what you can expect from this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debugging node.js in Cloud9 IDE</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/debugging-nodejs-in-cloud9-ide/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/debugging-nodejs-in-cloud9-ide/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In this article I&amp;rsquo;ll be sharing some of my level-up experience learning how to debug node.js apps. It was not easy at first, but once I got it, I felt empowered that now I can work with any code base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debugging is useful for solving vague problems in other people&amp;rsquo;s code and it&amp;rsquo;s also useful for learning how something actually works. The article might be particularly useful for those used to having debugger experience in WebStorm or similar IDEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;quick-reference&#34;&gt;Quick reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That article is meant to be more like a cheat sheet rather than too detailed step by step guide, here&amp;rsquo;s a go-to list of techniques:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;node-debugger&#34;&gt;Node debugger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start by the basics — using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://nodejs.org/api/debugger.html&#34;&gt;node&amp;rsquo;s native debugger&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Surnet/swagger-jsdoc/blob/master/example/app.js&#34;&gt;this app&lt;/a&gt; contains a simple server returning a JSON object which is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.be/url?sa=t&amp;amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiG4Pi0qfbOAhUEOhQKHaQICOAQFggcMAA&amp;amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fswagger.io%2Fspecification%2F&amp;amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNH_jZB7rkJVVCg-JHFmeLAHwMnUfw&amp;amp;amp;sig2=R2rG7_9EH1ctFeFwtJ7cPw&amp;amp;amp;bvm=bv.131783435,d.d24&#34;&gt;swagger specification&lt;/a&gt; and I need to debug and see its value. So, in this example, I&amp;rsquo;ll follow this steps to see the contents of the variable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a break point with &lt;code&gt;debugger&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the script with &lt;code&gt;node debug example/app.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work with the controls of the debugger to reach a good value: &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; to continue and &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; for next&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;repl&lt;/code&gt; to execute some code which access current state of the system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*CHRmYU912yZDRmqz7Z490w.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;simple-script&#34;&gt;Simple script&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a break point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press the Run button to execute the default node runner (ensure the debugger is enabled — &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/debugging-your-code&#34;&gt;more info&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*I-mVNLptBFDG-EaJpLR6rQ.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mocha-tests&#34;&gt;Mocha tests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/experimental-features&#34;&gt;experimental feature&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*-8oDjYBTEU4-G8H5_vw5lg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable &amp;lsquo;Tests&amp;rdquo; from the editor settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refresh the page and see the panel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put a break point in the test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable debugging in the &amp;ldquo;Test&amp;rdquo; panel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the test suite or scenario&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feature actually worked for me, I felt just the same way when I made my first &lt;a href=&#34;http://mortalkombat.wikia.com/wiki/Animality&#34;&gt;animality in MK3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*OHINaf_jcvN75EN1M0ozlQ.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;command-line-apps&#34;&gt;Command-line apps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact it&amp;rsquo;s almost identical to debugging a simple script, the only detail you have to notice is an input box where you put the actual command as if ran in the command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the command-line app and place a break point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the Run menu to start the process in debug more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the input process name and restart the runner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*V9xHSnqzwCasqzHiHyBD5Q.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;feedback-is-nbsp-welcome&#34;&gt;Feedback is&amp;nbsp;welcome&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the comments below to share your techniques and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud9 IDE – Digital Beer – Medium</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/cloud9-editor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/cloud9-editor/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*uc-REJYHbk02nuzVQmDHHQ.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few months ago I attended a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kalin.chernev/coding-battle-at-microsoft-innovation-center-brussels-the-rise-of-the-bots-f0887c15e257&#34;&gt;coding competition&lt;/a&gt;. In the end of the event the winners demonstrated one of their tools: the &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io&#34;&gt;Cloud9 editor&lt;/a&gt;. Then it hit me — I had to experiment with it! Later I used it working on various projects in my free time. Here I&amp;rsquo;m going to share my experience so far — I&amp;rsquo;m a happy user&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cloud9-is-nbsp-great&#34;&gt;Cloud9 is&amp;nbsp;great&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I&amp;rsquo;ve found several key points/facts why I consider the editor to be truly astounding tool:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility and User/Developer experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pair_programming&#34;&gt;Pair programming&lt;/a&gt; and education&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaboration and open source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accessibility&#34;&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool is currently &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/pricing&#34;&gt;free&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/c9&#34;&gt;open source&lt;/a&gt;. Even if you&amp;rsquo;re not a technical person you already have reason #1 to either make a &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/signup&#34;&gt;new registration&lt;/a&gt; or use your existing code-oriented account to &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/login&#34;&gt;log in&lt;/a&gt; to the service. (No affiliation in the links) If you are non-technical, but very business person, you might know that &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/blog/great-news/&#34;&gt;Amazon will probably grow Cloud9 in the future&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you are a technical person and you take a closer look, you&amp;rsquo;ll see that it&amp;rsquo;s a charming service of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ace.c9.io/#nav=about&#34;&gt;ace&lt;/a&gt; which directly accesses &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/&#34;&gt;docker&lt;/a&gt; instances. The first time I showed a working &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/create-a-workspace&#34;&gt;workspace&lt;/a&gt; to a friend developer telling him to use the environment just as Ubuntu — the response was something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*DBGdHlkB6DVjBy62d3TANQ.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, he setup all his bash aliases and specific configurations and started to work with the terminal just as he&amp;rsquo;s working with his own Linux machine&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pair-programming-and-education&#34;&gt;Pair programming and education&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the environment was ready (understand having all the aliases and custom shell scripts, drush, drupal console, etc. cli tools) we went into using some of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/share-a-workspace#section-collaboration-features&#34;&gt;collaboration features&lt;/a&gt;. I will not put a meme here, but I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you this: the experience is very similar to using Google Drive for collaborating on documents in real-time, so if you like this — you&amp;rsquo;ll surely like this real-time coding experience too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pair_programming&#34;&gt;Pair programming&lt;/a&gt; on same git branch and code base is not something we usually do for various reasons, but if you like doing it, or you need to do it — I&amp;rsquo;d definitely recommend you Cloud9. You can pair program remotely just as you&amp;rsquo;d normally do on 1 computer: sharing terminal, files, git branches, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these pair program opportunities come also very interesting education opportunities. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs50.harvard.edu/&#34;&gt;CS50&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.freecodecamp.com/challenges/start-a-nodejs-server&#34;&gt;freeCodeCamp&lt;/a&gt;. These are good case studies of the cloud editor to encourage people of all walks of life to give programming a try and learn their &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/supported-languages&#34;&gt;preferred programming language&lt;/a&gt; without any special computer hardware requirements, i.e. they can code real applications in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaboration-and-open-nbsp-source&#34;&gt;Collaboration and open&amp;nbsp;source&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the service is free and very fun to use, it&amp;rsquo;s naturally an optional tool when working on various projects requiring tight collaboration such as open source projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I decided to work on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Surnet/swagger-jsdoc&#34;&gt;swagger-jsdoc&lt;/a&gt; node module which I used for a small project. All I had to do to make a pull request is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a new workspace (new virtual machine in the cloud)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Git clone the fork repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new branch and do your task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push back to fork repository and open a pull request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I didn&amp;rsquo;t even have to install any software, all I had to make this contribution was to open my browser and use Cloud9 as a cloud service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;keybindings&#34;&gt;Keybindings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the items I&amp;rsquo;m using quite often and sometimes get a WOW effect from people watching me doing things like that in my browser:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/multiple-cursors&#34;&gt;Multiple cursors&lt;/a&gt; (yep, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sublimetext.com/&#34;&gt;sublime&lt;/a&gt; is to blame for our expectations)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Command line tricks work just well (Ctrl+U, Ctrl+L)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/keybindings&#34;&gt;Find in tree&lt;/a&gt; (and others)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/find-and-replacing-in-files#find-in-files&#34;&gt;Search/Find&lt;/a&gt; is handy working with namespaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think normally people don&amp;rsquo;t expect a full IDE experience in the browser, as I didn&amp;rsquo;t too, and that&amp;rsquo;s the reason I mentioned Docked previously for an eye-opener. Just by the way, PHP developers might be even more surprised with things like &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/blog/debug-your-php-code-with-xdebug-and-cloud9/&#34;&gt;xdebugger&lt;/a&gt; being available in their development environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;setting-up-drupal-nbsp-8&#34;&gt;Setting up Drupal&amp;nbsp;8&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might come even more shocking for people having an idea what &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drupal.org/&#34;&gt;Drupal&lt;/a&gt; is. It&amp;rsquo;s an association of heavy CMS with high resource demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, do the following the sake of having your WOW moment yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new workspace based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/drupal-composer/drupal-project&#34;&gt;Drupal Composer&lt;/a&gt; github repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the instructions to run an installation from the cli or the web (you might need to read &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.c9.io/t/setting-up-mysql/1718&#34;&gt;this MySQL&lt;/a&gt; article if you don&amp;rsquo;t have the idea to see your &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.ubuntu.com/community/EnvironmentVariables&#34;&gt;environment variables&lt;/a&gt; from the command line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profit from having a running Drupal 8 which uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://getcomposer.org/&#34;&gt;Composer&lt;/a&gt; scripts for managing modules and dependencies to external libraries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*12EXDc2rgRcy11wQk4SVjA.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>