<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Web Development on Kalin Chernev</title>
    <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/tags/web-development/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Web Development on Kalin Chernev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - 2017</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://kalinchernev.github.io/tags/web-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Think about apps, not websites</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/think-about-apps-not-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/think-about-apps-not-websites/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Admiring the progress of &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en/docs/Web/API&#34;&gt;Web APIs&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to shortly summarize some feelings. They are mostly about a borderline (common-sense) why it is worth knowing what is a web app and why we have to shift our paradigm thinking from building websites to building web apps. For this reason, I include few steps as a tutorial to encourage hands-on experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;state-of-internet&#34;&gt;State of internet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.internetlivestats.com/internet-users/#chart_trend&#34;&gt;more than 40% of the world has access to the Internet&lt;/a&gt;, and this number is yet to grow having in mind the vast popularity of campaigns which ensure that each one in the world is connected. It seems that we are in rush to make the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_village_%28term%29&#34;&gt;Global village reality&lt;/a&gt;. Yes, I still remember when making a dynamic website with mobile-friendly design was innovation, however, it’s simply &lt;a href=&#34;https://techcrunch.com/2014/08/21/majority-of-digital-media-consumption-now-takes-place-in-mobile-apps/&#34;&gt;not anything special any more&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, the digital world is much more accessible than before with smart-watches, smart-TVs, VRs, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Web as I envisaged it, we have not seen it yet. The future is still so much bigger than the past. —&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tim_Berners-Lee&#34;&gt;Tim Berners-Lee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reality-check&#34;&gt;Reality check&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the new software or hardware technologies do not make any sense if not used properly and effectively. For example, managing our user data and documents synchronization in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_computing&#34;&gt;the cloud&lt;/a&gt; is a vital skill you have to master. This way, you can take advantage of the technological opportunities of keeping your information safe and available anywhere you have a browser and an internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Docs,_Sheets_and_Slides&#34;&gt;Google docs&lt;/a&gt; got available to us a decade ago, and Microsoft followed with their &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OneDrive&#34;&gt;OneDrive&lt;/a&gt; few years later. So, regardless of the device (tablet, laptop, PC, etc.) we can work with our documents through our browser, AND have a safe backup of our work. Not taking advantage of cloud technologies to have synchronized backup of our important documents is a missed opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Making a website that shows only information is a missed opportunity.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is that? Well, simple — the problems we are solving today are different than the problems we were solving 10 years ago. Even if the criticism of the accelerated change were true, why would we encounter so many examples of transformation we did not anticipate with this speed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example higher user expectation: being able to work with mobile applications offline. A decade ago, a website was a good solution to having an online presence, i.e. having a business card, etc. Probably printing pages was ok. However, today, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pcworld.com/article/3145946/streaming-services/you-can-finally-watch-netflix-offline-now.html&#34;&gt;Netflix offline capabilities&lt;/a&gt; or editing documents in Google Drive offline mode are making customers happy, because users are mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In similar conditions, building a website to just share information is not something special any more, because users expect a whole different, more engaging digital experience — think about SMS notifications. They were standard some years ago, but not anymore. Today, push notifications are everywhere. And there is no way that trend goes down, as the future connected world will involve even higher amount of notifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;web-apps&#34;&gt;Web apps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Web apps” is probably something you already know. Web apps are consisted of HTML, CSS and JavaScript. Difference between them and regular websites, is that the same technologies are used with “spices”: new methods to achieve better results. Meet the Progressive Web Apps, aka &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/&#34;&gt;PWA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term has been around for awhile, so starter tutorials are accessible:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/getting-started/codelabs/your-first-pwapp/&#34;&gt;Your first PWA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2016/12/progressive-web-amps/&#34;&gt;Progressive Web AMPs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2016/08/a-beginners-guide-to-progressive-web-apps/&#34;&gt;A beginners guide to PWA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2016/09/the-building-blocks-of-progressive-web-apps/&#34;&gt;The Building Blocks Of Progressive Web Apps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, there are many benefits of adding an some extra efforts into your existing (or new) web pages to make them available in bad network conditions (when offline), and provide functionalities that are normally expected by users in mobile, but in the browser. And browsers are something you have almost everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a decision maker or a company owner with a business around &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.chromium.org/2016/08/from-chrome-apps-to-web.html&#34;&gt;Chrome Apps or extensions&lt;/a&gt;, you have an even bigger motivation to follow this trend, in order to maintain your business in near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, get into the habit to use your browser effectively as a tool in your skill-set of the future :) Even if you are not a developer, you have to imagine that at some point of time, &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/swlh/browsers-not-apps-are-the-future-of-mobile-c552752ff75#.ackczpqrj&#34;&gt;the browser will be the app you are running everywhere&lt;/a&gt; regardless of your operating system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And a bonus for seasoned developers reaching this point of the article: this &lt;a href=&#34;https://auth0.com/blog/chromedevsummit-summary/&#34;&gt;summary of chrome dev summit&lt;/a&gt; would be worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;making-a-web-app&#34;&gt;Making a web app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve marked some initial milestones that worked for me, the order shouldn’t be important, but that’s more or less how I see the process — hopefully easy to understand and follow with a bit of hands-on practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be going through the most popular and basic features of PWA which could complement existing websites and make them more app-like. I believe that gradual improvements in existing websites is a good strategy for making the best of the modern web, while avoiding regressions in working solutions. This way, everybody win — business owners invest smartly into new enhancements, developers upgrade their solutions taking small doable steps, also, the end-user (the king) receives improved experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what we want to achieve is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User can save our application to his phone for quick access&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User can open the application without access to the Internet, and still see meaningful contents that help him continue working with the application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;devtools&#34;&gt;DevTools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before kicking off the tutorial part, please, use Google Chrome while working out the rest of the items — ensuring you have really great experience and least amount of hurdles on browser support during your journey. Firefox, Edge and Opera could be alternatives, however, Chrome has the best support for modern JavaScript at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This video is an entertaining summary of the documentation about &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/tools/chrome-devtools/progressive-web-apps&#34;&gt;debugging progressive web apps with Chrome DevTools&lt;/a&gt;. Most certainly, general familiarity with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/tools/chrome-devtools/&#34;&gt;DevTools&lt;/a&gt; would help you understand it, although the panel for debugging PWA is much simpler than the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IWgNn1kqrsA?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;create-a-manifest-file&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a manifest file&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manifest file should comply to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://w3c.github.io/manifest/&#34;&gt;specification&lt;/a&gt; which serves a similar purpose as of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.chrome.com/extensions/manifest&#34;&gt;Chrome Platform API manifest file&lt;/a&gt; — it&amp;rsquo;s a set of definitions. &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/updates/2015/03/increasing-engagement-with-app-install-banners-in-chrome-for-android&#34;&gt;The installation of a web app&lt;/a&gt; is more engaging than the one of a native app, i.e. one doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to go to a &amp;ldquo;store&amp;rdquo;, but take it right away. Note that a service worker file should be loaded (and activated, etc.) to achieve this interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*DYjPm6A9VuxueEU7mD_lPQ.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image taken from&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/updates/2015/03/increasing-engagement-with-app-install-banners-in-chrome-for-android&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing this article, these are the criteria:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;definition manifest file is present&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the manifest file contains at least the following properties: &lt;code&gt;short_name&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;144x144&lt;/code&gt; PNG icon with its corresponding mime type meta info&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;app is served over HTTPS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The user has visited your site at least twice, with at least five minutes between visits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, this year &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.android.com/topic/instant-apps/index.html&#34;&gt;instant apps&lt;/a&gt; were announced. They are something similar for Android native apps. It seems like a unified direction into making the content and functionalities more accessible for the user. For the install, If you have a native app, and you want to suggest it to the user, &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/updates/2015/03/increasing-engagement-with-app-install-banners-in-chrome-for-android#native&#34;&gt;use the manifest for this&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/engage-and-retain/push-notifications/good-notification#dont-advertise-native&#34;&gt;do NOT advertise the native app via a push notification&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To try and experiment with this basic step, take either any of the tutorials in &lt;a href=&#34;https://codelabs.developers.google.com/&#34;&gt;codelabs&lt;/a&gt; or by use &lt;a href=&#34;https://googlesamples.github.io/&#34;&gt;sample snippets&lt;/a&gt; (don&amp;rsquo;t really know if it&amp;rsquo;s the same as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.chromestatus.com/samples&#34;&gt;chrome samples&lt;/a&gt;), or just clone &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kalinchernev/pwa/tree/basics/manifest&#34;&gt;this branch&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m personally using &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kalin.chernev/cloud9-ide-6e26940c6130#.cotqpyn8b&#34;&gt;cloud9 editor&lt;/a&gt; for development, as it serves the applications over HTTPS by default, which is really convenient to just go and try things. There are many alternatives for both the editor and server: just choose what works best for you and don&amp;rsquo;t over-think or over-prepare, focus on the doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of this, you must already have a feeling of achievement! Creating a manifest file that loads some assets and an empty JavaScript file is easy, but rewarding enough to keep your momentum to continue further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are like me, testing the behavior of &amp;ldquo;Add to homescreen&amp;rdquo; in both the desktop browser and the mobile phone, you will surely notice that &amp;ldquo;homescreen&amp;rdquo; of the browser is the browser&amp;rsquo;s home of apps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*L63xgn3aL-6YTv7LnpwpVQ.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;add to homescreen behavior on your desktop&amp;nbsp;browser&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.w3.org/TR/appmanifest/#dfn-display-mode&#34;&gt;`display mode&lt;/a&gt;` the app can run in a separate standalone window that looks like a desktop app (and in mobile it looks like mobile), by hiding the address bar. This is how &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.chrome.com/apps/about_apps&#34;&gt;Chrome Apps&lt;/a&gt; should be build in the future too, not only websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*mowO5VIVEwFBcOJcXY4OUQ.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same app open in a normal browser and in a standalone window&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same code (HTML+CSS+manifest file and an empty JavaScript file loaded as a service worker) produce good mobile experience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*qDNI5CsWyWWPty5qcM6KaA.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add to home screen is same as installing the app on the&amp;nbsp;device&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the icon is added to the desktop as expected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*u1QOfgyz4iEdl1dZ2zrDPg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and when the icon is clicked, the user gets a nice welcoming screen, colors defined as &lt;code&gt;theme_color&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;background_color&lt;/code&gt; properties in the manifest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*HLOcyRrmJu2AvKN4aqrlCQ.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, in standalone display mode, no URL address bar is visible. Use a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?q=best+mobile-first+CSS+frameworks+today&#34;&gt;good front-end framework&lt;/a&gt; to make the look and feel of your web page as a native app — the user will be delighted!&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-app-nbsp-shell&#34;&gt;The app&amp;nbsp;shell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s mostly conceptual yet important task to think about: in order to deliver good user experience, it&amp;rsquo;s useful to have access to fundamental assets offline in order to react well in case of a network going offline. So, when you build and develop your web site, consider it&amp;rsquo;s a real shell that stays the same and only the contents is changing. This article gives good &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/architecture/app-shell&#34;&gt;concept overview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not something super-new for people who are used to thinking about apps already, or developers of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-page_application&#34;&gt;SPAs&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s just something to always have in the back of your mind when you look at your own website — what resources are important to deliver to the user even when he&amp;rsquo;s offline? What are the repetitive elements of my web pages? Normally these are the navigation and its surroundings. All these become the &amp;ldquo;shell&amp;rdquo;, being cached on the device for easy access, and the content is dynamically fetched when available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*dEvx7lPNJT-r-tKjqvAXxg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/architecture/app-shell&#34;&gt;Image credits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to implement this strategy for saving resources, one must know how to use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Cache&#34;&gt;Cache API&lt;/a&gt; through a service worker. The API can also be accessed through the global &lt;code&gt;window&lt;/code&gt; object as well, but working through a SW, we can &amp;ldquo;hook&amp;rdquo; into the events in the worker&amp;rsquo;s life-cycle, i.e. we can validate cache when network connection toggles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;creating-a-servic-worker&#34;&gt;Creating a servic worker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rich offline experiences, periodic background syncs, push notifications — functionality that would normally require a native application — are coming to the web. Service workers provide the technical foundation that all these features rely on. — taken from &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/getting-started/primers/service-workers&#34;&gt;Service Workers: an Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In basic terms, the service worker is a proxy layer between your stack (HTML+CSS+JS) and the network. The API of service workers boost the functionality of your otherwise normal web pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good starting point could be the sample for &lt;a href=&#34;https://googlechrome.github.io/samples/service-worker/custom-offline-page/index.html&#34;&gt;Service Worker Sample: Custom Offline Page Sample&lt;/a&gt;. If the amount of code seems too much, have a look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/tools/service-worker-libraries/&#34;&gt;tools section&lt;/a&gt; where some libraries are already published to make these functionalities more accessible. For example, if your project uses a task runner, you can implement &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/GoogleChrome/sw-precache#install&#34;&gt;`sw-precache&lt;/a&gt;` (&lt;a href=&#34;https://codelabs.developers.google.com/codelabs/sw-precache/#0&#34;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; is also available&amp;nbsp;;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, personally, it was fun to play a bit with the service worker file, not having access to the DOM directly, but yet having a Web API that should communicate with it was an interesting thing. In the end, I used the example code provided in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/GoogleChrome/sw-precache/tree/master/demo&#34;&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;code&gt;sw-precache&lt;/code&gt; because I&amp;rsquo;m really lazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the exercise, I have this branch for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kalinchernev/pwa/tree/basics/caching&#34;&gt;the basics of caching the application shell&lt;/a&gt;. What I really like as a side-effect of stealing the gulp file of the demo above is that now I have a basic build system. That helps me in generating a comparatively sophisticated service-worker handling the offline behavior of my web app. Also, it gives me a nicely working &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;gh-pages website&lt;/a&gt; that can be accessed by anyone over HTTPS on &lt;https: kalinchernev.github.io=&#34;&#34; pwa=&#34;&#34;&gt; This makes me really happy, because of several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I already have a self-hosted, manageable (easy to update and deploy), modern web app, that looks like a mobile app. It can be viewed and installed on a mobile device, and later opened in a &amp;ldquo;shell&amp;rdquo;, i.e. not showing broken pages offline mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a task runner like &lt;a href=&#34;http://gulpjs.com/&#34;&gt;gulp&lt;/a&gt; opens a door of opportunities to make my development life even easier than before: I can integrate live reload, include any preprocessing of LESS/SASS, can include babel to turn my ES6 code in ES5 for older browsers, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the &lt;code&gt;sw-precache&lt;/code&gt; even as simple as it is right now, provides me with benefits of easier asset management, as I don&amp;rsquo;t have to go too much into the details of the Cache API if I don&amp;rsquo;t want to, and the mechanism of implementing the worker is easier to update in the future, as I believe the project will be well maintained. So, my task for future maintenance will be to re-generate the worker which is already included on the page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that you already see more opportunities than before. In particular, next time you want to publish information that is important and useful for your users when, say, they travel, consider these options. Imagine you want to provide accessible guides and documentation — just follow the same steps and provide enhanced experience, I&amp;rsquo;m sure it&amp;rsquo;ll pay off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;push-notification&#34;&gt;Push notification&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me briefly indicate some resources that I consider useful for the topic, without going into details, as this feature is going a bit beyond the browser and won&amp;rsquo;t be as beginner-friendly as I&amp;rsquo;d like it to be. This topic deserves another separate article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a start, you can start with &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/getting-started/codelabs/push-notifications/&#34;&gt;Adding Push Notifications to a Web App&lt;/a&gt;. It can be well-complemented with &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en/docs/Web/API/Push_API/Using_the_Push_API&#34;&gt;Using the Push API&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/dev-channel/designing-a-web-push-service-3076c0599f3e#.6xi4d77ds&#34;&gt;Designing a Web Push Service&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@paul_kinlan&#34;&gt;Paul Kinlan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from being bright, it will be filled with advancements and further variety in the developers&amp;rsquo; toolbox. Having in mind that browsers have always been an inconsistent environment, it will be vital to keep the following resources at hand and get fresh information every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to underline, that &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@nekrtemplar/progressive-web-apps-aint-google-s-thing-31ca581e7a1#.faazl83yx&#34;&gt;Progressive Web Apps isn&amp;rsquo;t a Google-only thing&lt;/a&gt; although many of the references in this article are going to resources authored by community contributions to Google documentation. This is mainly because the dedication and organization of knowledge seems to the best at the moment. &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.windows.com/msedgedev/2016/07/08/the-progress-of-web-apps/#ZeJAshXJM2BuqDRB.97&#34;&gt;Microsoft are also supporters of PWA&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;http://manifoldjs.com&#34;&gt;manifoldjs&lt;/a&gt; is an interesting project you will probably meet should you decide to make PWA that works as a nice app in Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, Web APIs will surely continue to evolve. You can bookmark the good ol&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://caniuse.com/#search=push&#34;&gt;caniuse.com&lt;/a&gt; to verify whether an API you want to use is supported natively or you&amp;rsquo;ll have to search for a shim/polyfill and similar. Of course, there are many existing libraries and frameworks which are already taking developers attention (causing fatigue&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I speak about experimental features that will change, but I firmly believe that browser vendors are on a good way of collaborating to support native APIs more consistently rapidly in very near future, so these features will be standard before you realize it. Knowing the standards helps you produce more maintainable code and gives you a good idea about the direction of Web, regardless of the popularity and influence of vendor frameworks and libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are simple steps that anyone can take in order to convert their existing websites and web pages in progressive web apps, i.e. pages with HTML+CSS+JavaScript which act like native apps for important functionalities. Installation, caching and push notifications are a growing trend for a reason — they increase user engagement and provide great experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, during the upcoming holidays, have a look at the following Web APIs, and hopefully play with them, provide more value via your web pages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a &lt;code&gt;manifest.json&lt;/code&gt; file describing your app with its assets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;implement caching for the vital assets necessary when offline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make a simple push notification for events of new content on your pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, using native Web APIs will be fun during this experimentation, as &lt;a href=&#34;http://kangax.github.io/compat-table/es6/&#34;&gt;Chrome supports a lot of ES6 features&lt;/a&gt; and there is no need for you to transpile your code to see immediate results of your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy and good luck!&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drupal 8 on Cloud9 IDE</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/drupal8-cloud9-ide/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/drupal8-cloud9-ide/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;You see things; and you say, &amp;lsquo;Why?&amp;rsquo; But I dream things that never were; and I say, &amp;lsquo;Why not?&amp;ldquo; — George Bernard Shaw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drupal.org/8&#34;&gt;Drupal 8&lt;/a&gt; will soon celebrate 1 year since its release. One interesting fact about this version of the popular PHP CMS is that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drupal.org/core/release-cycle-overview&#34;&gt;release cycles&lt;/a&gt; are smaller and feature-focused. This makes everybody happier than previous major versions and I will focus on developers&amp;rsquo; experience. It&amp;rsquo;s been steadily improving since the focused adoption of popular and well-maintained projects from the wide PHP community. &lt;a href=&#34;https://getcomposer.org/&#34;&gt;Composer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://drupalconsole.com/&#34;&gt;Drupal Console&lt;/a&gt; (an implementation of Symfony Console) and adopting PHP OOP design patterns in overall are some of the highlights in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, &lt;a href=&#34;http://c9.io&#34;&gt;Cloud9 Editor&lt;/a&gt; is an interesting project to my personal experience as a developer. I&amp;rsquo;ve shared some enthusiasm about it before, summarizing &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kalin.chernev/cloud9-ide-6e26940c6130#.nxqgf2ree&#34;&gt;some of my favorite features&lt;/a&gt;, and going deeper into &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kalin.chernev/debugging-node-js-in-cloud9-ide-59712c043fb2#.tknem3kcp&#34;&gt;debugging applications in the cloud&lt;/a&gt;. At this step, I start to dream about scenarios where this cloud editor will be THE editor for massive amount of open source contributors, experimenters and agile practitioners alike. I also visualize scenarios where it could fill in the gap in the hearts of many who use tools like &lt;a href=&#34;https://dreditor.org/&#34;&gt;dreditor&lt;/a&gt;. Dreditor on steroids: git, drush, mysql, php, etc — all the tools a developer needs to start, test, develop and deploy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;repository-based-development-environment&#34;&gt;Repository based development environment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/drupal-composer/drupal-project&#34;&gt;Drupal Composer&amp;rsquo;s drupal-project&lt;/a&gt; seems like a really interesting repository which can enable me to start a Drupal 8 project and make an installation. Also it will provide me with a door of opportunities to manage all my project-global dependencies via composer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I can do to start a &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/getting-started&#34;&gt;Cloud9 workspace&lt;/a&gt; linked my own fork repository of the drupal-project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forked the original repo to my own &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kalinchernev/drupal-project&#34;&gt;drupal-project repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new workspace pointing to the my fork repo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Selecting template &amp;ldquo;The popular stack in shiny cloud wrappings: Apache, PHP5 and MySQL pre-configured&amp;rdquo; seems ok for the moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should look similar to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*nbj-D9ufx-wlGZ-MdBj6Jw.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating my new development environment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of this process, I have an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ubuntu.com/&#34;&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;-based &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/&#34;&gt;docker&lt;/a&gt; container. In it, there is a local repository linked to my upstream repository on the origin. I&amp;rsquo;m ready to use the tools I know in Linux because composer, npm, node, etc. are already installed, and I also have a command line interface to run or install anything I need on top of this initial setup. As a side note, &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/community/templates&#34;&gt;custom templates&lt;/a&gt; will soon make this initial setup even more flexible and personalized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the terminal is already open for you, run &lt;code&gt;git remote -v&lt;/code&gt; to ensure this origin linking if you like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;selecting-drupal-nbsp-8&#34;&gt;Selecting Drupal&amp;nbsp;8&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the workspace is ready, you have to select a branch for the Drupal version you are going to work with. I&amp;rsquo;m going to do &lt;code&gt;git checkout 8.x&lt;/code&gt; in the ternimal to use the 8.x version of the the repository files in the container machine. When you do that, you&amp;rsquo;ll see the files in the tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Eoo2-TstzN_2AtY1m4kagw.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drupal 8 branch of the repository&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the source files I can use to build the project with the dependencies and the tools of my personal preference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;building-project-dependencies&#34;&gt;Building project dependencies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dependencies can be &lt;a href=&#34;https://getcomposer.org/doc/00-intro.md#dependency-management&#34;&gt;managed globally for the project&lt;/a&gt; via the composer.json file. What interests me the most are the Drupal, Drupal Console and Drush which are already &lt;a href=&#34;https://getcomposer.org/doc/01-basic-usage.md#the-require-key&#34;&gt;required&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*3AcZBLBGsVdelfdFPJcmMw.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drupal-specific initial dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the readme file of the repo points out, additional dependencies can be added later by &lt;a href=&#34;https://getcomposer.org/doc/01-basic-usage.md#installing-dependencies&#34;&gt;installing dependencies through the composer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run &lt;code&gt;composer install&lt;/code&gt; in the terminal to download all the dependencies and run all the composer special things defined in the composer.json file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When all downloads are finished — you can just run the Run button and start the apache server in the machine to open the project in the project browser or your own browser:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*Wk4VtthU1g6TbvI70Q7u3Q.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open the project in the browser after the dependencies installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you resist your perfectionist nature and expectations on domain names, now you can open the project at &lt;a href=&#34;https://%7Bprojectname%7D-%7Busername%7D.c9users.io/web/core/install.php&#34;&gt;https://{projectname}-{username}.c9users.io/web/core/install.php&lt;/a&gt; replacing the variables of course. And there you go, you have Drupal 8 ready for your install!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*ZOtYTj11S-Mi9h_894NoMA.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep, the wizard is&amp;nbsp;ready!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;installing-the-nbsp-project&#34;&gt;Installing the&amp;nbsp;project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I deliberately left this out from the previous one. You can, of course, continue with the installation in the most user-friendly way with the wizard above. Classical and easy and you don&amp;rsquo;t worry even for file permissions. If you are a databases guy, probably you&amp;rsquo;ll be interested to check the tutorial for &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.c9.io/t/setting-up-mysql/1718&#34;&gt;setting up mysql&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/setup-a-database&#34;&gt;setting up a database&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option for making the installation is using the command line interface and Drupal Console. If you&amp;rsquo;re a non-idealist developer, you can directly run the binary from the vendor folder like &lt;code&gt;/vendor/bin/drupal&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*dx0IRYUqpwRv512zYSBGJg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drupal Console initialization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will hint you to run an initial setup for the tool, just do it and then you can have &lt;a href=&#34;https://hechoendrupal.gitbooks.io/drupal-console/content/en/commands/site-install.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vendor/bin/drupal site:install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more ideas around this installation step, check &lt;a href=&#34;https://drupalconsole.com/articles/how-to-download-and-install-drupal-8-using-drupal-console&#34;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt; which also includes steps to download the project if it was not done by Composer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shooting some ideas of a quick-start yml file for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.drupalconsole.com/en/commands/chain.html&#34;&gt;`chain&lt;/a&gt;`.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-yaml&#34;&gt;commands:
# Install Drupal
  - command: site:install
    options:
      langcode: &#39;en&#39;
      db-type: &#39;%{{db_type|mysql}}&#39;
      db-host: &#39;%{{db_host|127.0.0.1}}&#39;
      db-name: &#39;%{{db_name|c9}}&#39;
      db-user: &#39;%{{db_user|root}}&#39;
      db-pass: &#39;%{{db_pass|}}&#39;
      db-port: &#39;%{{db_port|3306}}&#39;
      site-name: &#39;Drupal 8 site&#39;
      site-mail: &#39;admin@example.org&#39; # default email
      account-name: &#39;admin&#39; # default account
      account-mail: &#39;admin@example.org&#39; # default email
      account-pass: &#39;admin&#39; # default pass
    arguments:
      profile: &#39;standard&#39;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;debugging&#34;&gt;Debugging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small helper subject after the setup — since xdebug is available in the docker in &amp;ldquo;Apache &amp;amp; PHP&amp;rdquo; runner, there is a way to debug apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start &amp;ldquo;Apache &amp;amp; PHP&amp;rdquo; runner with debugger on:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*ksgXbNGH5Lp_HtVdLoQWMA.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The green debugger button is the important detail to&amp;nbsp;notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a break-point and open the application to trigger a request:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*26fDzn9eaCW1fwMcB9BSEQ.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app can be run either in preview in the IDE or in another&amp;nbsp;tab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inspect the state of the system and profit from deeper understanding&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*lfPKCwwocB8NkegBzv7fOA.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the inspector for observing both global and local&amp;nbsp;scopes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the runner properties can be edited:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*m1WawXoob6Jg7DiUIlN9hg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Runners are editable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// This file overrides the built-in Apache httpd (PHP, HTML) runner
// For more information see http://docs.c9.io:8080/#!/api/run-method-run
{
  &amp;quot;cmd&amp;quot;: [
    &amp;quot;run-apache2&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;${debug?debug}&amp;quot;
  ],
  &amp;quot;cmdStop&amp;quot;: [
    &amp;quot;run-apache2&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;stop&amp;quot;
  ],
  &amp;quot;debugger&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;xdebug&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;debugport&amp;quot;: 9000,
  &amp;quot;$debugDefaultState&amp;quot;: false,
  &amp;quot;selector&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;^.*\\.(php|phtml|html|shtml)$&amp;quot;,
  &amp;quot;env&amp;quot;: {
    &amp;quot;XDEBUG_CONFIG&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;xdebug.remote_enable=1 idekey=cloud9ide remote_host=localhost remote_port=9000 remote_mode=req&amp;quot;
  },
  &amp;quot;info&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Starting Apache httpd, serving \\033[01;34m$hostname_path\\033[00m.&amp;quot;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an ambitious initiative/dream to work with Drupal 8 projects in the cloud but you see that it&amp;rsquo;s possible and easy. In the end of this tutorial you have a working instance built out of a composer-based dependency management system, your custom repository, and the vital tools to help you develop well: Drupal Console, Drush and any other script you can think of that run on an Ubuntu machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;rsquo;s up to you to use these tools to your best interest: teaching Drupal 8 interactively, pair-programming, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drupal.org/contributor-tasks/triage-novice-issues&#34;&gt;triage&lt;/a&gt; issues by making/testing patches or just experimenting with features you&amp;rsquo;re interested in anywhere, anytime.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coding battle with Skygate @MolenGeek</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/coding-battle-molengeek/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/coding-battle-molengeek/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The last event from the series of coding battles organized by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.philos.io/&#34;&gt;Philos&lt;/a&gt;, this time in cooperation with Skygate on a life-saving topic using tools like Google Maps and Firebase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/denisomelcenco&#34;&gt;Denis Omelcenco&lt;/a&gt; from Skygate presented the challenge: make an app to locate the closest defibrillator. The initial code base contained helpful starting materials such as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DenisSkygate/CodingBattle/blob/master/Defibrillators.json&#34;&gt;JSON file listing the defibrillators&lt;/a&gt; and their locations, together with some &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DenisSkygate/CodingBattle&#34;&gt;HTML files&lt;/a&gt; to facilitate the app building. Also, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/maxczet&#34;&gt;Max&lt;/a&gt; provided additional helpful resources on &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/maps/&#34;&gt;Google Maps API&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.firebase.com/&#34;&gt;Firebase&lt;/a&gt;, etc. As you can imagine, the topic inspired the developers since it&amp;rsquo;s based on meaningful cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the spirit of &amp;ldquo;Never too early to start&amp;rdquo;, there was a very young participant. I wish this inspires more lads and ladies to join in next events&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*ZiiIav-nONmY-C8LqOIxdw.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-tools&#34;&gt;The tools&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Google Maps API&lt;/strong&gt; was the easiest for the developers, probably because it&amp;rsquo;s a popular tool many of us had used before. Needless to say, good start examples were present, together with many answers on the internet on how to handle the various topics like directions, geo-locations, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firebase&lt;/strong&gt; was a new tool for my team. The tool came super-handy on building an API based on an existing &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.firebase.com/docs/rest/quickstart.html&#34;&gt;JSON really really easy&lt;/a&gt;. The only step necessary was to normalize the key:value pairs to have good naming for the import. Otherwise, we built a RESTful back-end with data about defibrillators in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.apple.com/swift/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swift&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was also useful tool for some who decided to build a native app&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*EEgjG4Ja_L5iScKDLYM2Yg.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;winners-and-working-nbsp-apps&#34;&gt;Winners and working&amp;nbsp;apps&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, there were 2 working apps: the one with Swift, and one with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DenisSkygate&#34;&gt;the &amp;ldquo;starterkit&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. The final presentations of the projects gave some insights on the Google Maps APIs used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*A5RYiojFrUUUxRklNiRT8Q.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;time-to-enjoy-the-summer-nbsp&#34;&gt;Time to enjoy the summer&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next event will be somewhere in September, but it&amp;rsquo;s not fixed yet because of the forthcoming summer months. To get notified for the next editions, just sign in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/javascriptlab/&#34;&gt;meetup group&lt;/a&gt; or in the facebook group page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Philos we saw a growing community and interest of hacking making small useful apps in very short time. Wish them luck and more opportunities for organizing even bigger projects in the future!&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*T1IwXqRxsa26rQ2Wu1Sf8A.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The first coding battle in Belgium</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/first-coding-battle-belgium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/first-coding-battle-belgium/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coding-battle-what&#34;&gt;Coding? Battle? What?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, coding is an act of expressing ways of thinking and problem-solving skills. However, in reality, it&amp;rsquo;s a more than that. It&amp;rsquo;s a proof of understanding complex concepts, and creating useful solutions with this understanding. Also, in fact, coding is frequently an act of showing narrow knowledge of a specific framework or knowledge of an API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Battles, on the other hand, are not an every-day thing. Rap battles and games are fun though, why not take the same experience into another subject matter as an expression of quick-thinking and winning attitude?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining those, one can already enjoy online platforms like &lt;a href=&#34;https://codefights.com/&#34;&gt;codefights.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens in offline, face-to-face world though?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;coding-battle&#34;&gt;Coding battle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s an opportunity to get experience actively. Battling is not only about watching a presentation, but solving problems. Quickly. And effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going into a battle is a learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-organizers&#34;&gt;The organizers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.philos.io/&#34;&gt;Philos Lab&lt;/a&gt; is a frequent organizer of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/javascriptlab/&#34;&gt;JavaScript events&lt;/a&gt; around Belgium, Netherlands, Luxembourg and France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.woorank.com/&#34;&gt;Woorank&lt;/a&gt; is a product-oriented company who kindly prepared the challenges and hosted the battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, they organized the first coding battle in Brussels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-battle&#34;&gt;The battle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was more enjoyable than you might think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I was doubtful about my own skills and readiness to go into a competition. That&amp;rsquo;s because JavaScript is changing every day, learning fatigue is something normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this competition, developers had to program a bot, playing against a dealer bot based on this &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Woorank/blackjack-challenge&#34;&gt;blackjack challenge&lt;/a&gt;. The rules were simple, there were teams (4 rounds by 4), playing against each other on playoffs principle. The better ratio of games won vs games lost ruled winning teams to the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I enjoyed the challenge. It didn&amp;rsquo;t require any previous knowledge of frameworks like Angular or React, but rather assumed general knowledge: variables, scope, functions and loops. That was really important in terms of facilitating the teams to focus on strategic thinking programming their automated bots, rather frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe these characteristics of the challenge were truly important. In the end, it was not really about whether or not developers know JavaScript or frameworks deeply, but rather: can developers understand requirements, code and logic quickly (2 hours and 30 minutes :), and provide solutions based on mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-did-i-nbsp-learn&#34;&gt;What did I&amp;nbsp;learn&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Re-consider understanding the core algorithms&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of 2 hours and 30 minutes, I spent maybe around 40 minutes trying to figure out the structure of the code of the &amp;ldquo;dealer&amp;rdquo;. (the server) That might have been useful if I knew specifically that my results/winning will be evaluated based on understanding other people&amp;rsquo;s code. That&amp;rsquo;s not impossible, but takes a lot of time! Take-away: listen carefully for the expectations. Reading and understanding API-s as-is is not helping in a battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s useful to know the subject matter of the challenge, i.e. blackjack. Though every challenge will be different, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t focus on this in my next challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Focus on super-clear communication&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It happens every day, it happens in battles as well — discussing scope, persistence and making use of history of actions for future actions. There is no place for bad communication in a battle. Global scope is so much not an object scope. And dependency injection is not always possible, don&amp;rsquo;t take it for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Focus on mathematics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though I don&amp;rsquo;t take myself as an expert in algorithms, making mathematical model of if-else-s is important. Me and my team-mate did not have any idea what a blackjack is, but we googled for strategies we translated into mathematics we implemented: and we ended up in the finals. You really have to experience this to believe it: creating code with clear mathematics that solves problems for you is beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Team-work is important&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No need to go too deep into this. I was lucky with this one during the particular event. I worked together with a colleague I work with every day&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Splitting down the small details was a breeze: which functions should do what, why, how, etc. The action was so hot that at some point using the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Statements/for...of&#34;&gt;for of&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; syntax fit perfectly for the general foreach() equivalent for the major chunk for the decider logic. Believe me, there is no time to re-factor, questions like sugar in JS: Class vs Function, public method of a module vs private method of an instance are too tiny of topics in dynamic circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://kalinchernev.github.io/images/coding-battle-code.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Team work during coding event&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;community&#34;&gt;Community&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In overall, the big winning was absolutely going into the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://kalinchernev.github.io/images/coding-battle-community.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Community&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good-bye picture at the spacious Woorank&amp;nbsp;office&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;bragging-time&#34;&gt;Bragging time&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this competition, my team reached the finals, team-6&amp;nbsp;;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://kalinchernev.github.io/images/coding-battle-table.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;Blackjack table&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &amp;ldquo;table&amp;rdquo; server where bots (teams) play against a dealer&amp;nbsp;(bot)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>