<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Javascript on Kalin Chernev</title>
    <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/tags/javascript/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Javascript on Kalin Chernev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - 2017</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://kalinchernev.github.io/tags/javascript/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Think about apps, not websites</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/think-about-apps-not-websites/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/think-about-apps-not-websites/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;create-a-manifest-nbsp-file&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a manifest&amp;nbsp;file&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manifest file should comply to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://w3c.github.io/manifest/&#34;&gt;specification&lt;/a&gt; which serves a similar purpose as of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.chrome.com/extensions/manifest&#34;&gt;Chrome Platform API manifest file&lt;/a&gt; — it&amp;rsquo;s a set of definitions. &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/updates/2015/03/increasing-engagement-with-app-install-banners-in-chrome-for-android&#34;&gt;The installation of a web app&lt;/a&gt; is more engaging than the one of a native app, i.e. one doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to go to a &amp;ldquo;store&amp;rdquo;, but take it right away. Note that a service worker file should be loaded (and activated, etc.) to achieve this interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*DYjPm6A9VuxueEU7mD_lPQ.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Image taken from&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/updates/2015/03/increasing-engagement-with-app-install-banners-in-chrome-for-android&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing this article, these are the criteria:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;definition manifest file is present&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the manifest file contains at least the following properties: &lt;code&gt;short_name&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;144x144&lt;/code&gt; PNG icon with its corresponding mime type meta info&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;app is served over HTTPS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The user has visited your site at least twice, with at least five minutes between visits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, this year &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.android.com/topic/instant-apps/index.html&#34;&gt;instant apps&lt;/a&gt; were announced. They are something similar for Android native apps. It seems like a unified direction into making the content and functionalities more accessible for the user. For the install, If you have a native app, and you want to suggest it to the user, &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/updates/2015/03/increasing-engagement-with-app-install-banners-in-chrome-for-android#native&#34;&gt;use the manifest for this&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/engage-and-retain/push-notifications/good-notification#dont-advertise-native&#34;&gt;do NOT advertise the native app via a push notification&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To try and experiment with this basic step, take either any of the tutorials in &lt;a href=&#34;https://codelabs.developers.google.com/&#34;&gt;codelabs&lt;/a&gt; or by use &lt;a href=&#34;https://googlesamples.github.io/&#34;&gt;sample snippets&lt;/a&gt; (don&amp;rsquo;t really know if it&amp;rsquo;s the same as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.chromestatus.com/samples&#34;&gt;chrome samples&lt;/a&gt;), or just clone &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kalinchernev/pwa/tree/basics/manifest&#34;&gt;this branch&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m personally using &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kalin.chernev/cloud9-ide-6e26940c6130#.cotqpyn8b&#34;&gt;cloud9 editor&lt;/a&gt; for development, as it serves the applications over HTTPS by default, which is really convenient to just go and try things. There are many alternatives for both the editor and server: just choose what works best for you and don&amp;rsquo;t over-think or over-prepare, focus on the doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of this, you must already have a feeling of achievement! Creating a manifest file that loads some assets and an empty JavaScript file is easy, but rewarding enough to keep your momentum to continue further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are like me, testing the behavior of &amp;ldquo;Add to homescreen&amp;rdquo; in both the desktop browser and the mobile phone, you will surely notice that &amp;ldquo;homescreen&amp;rdquo; of the browser is the browser&amp;rsquo;s home of apps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*L63xgn3aL-6YTv7LnpwpVQ.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;add to homescreen behavior on your desktop&amp;nbsp;browser&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.w3.org/TR/appmanifest/#dfn-display-mode&#34;&gt;`display mode&lt;/a&gt;` the app can run in a separate standalone window that looks like a desktop app (and in mobile it looks like mobile), by hiding the address bar. This is how &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.chrome.com/apps/about_apps&#34;&gt;Chrome Apps&lt;/a&gt; should be build in the future too, not only websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*mowO5VIVEwFBcOJcXY4OUQ.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same app open in a normal browser and in a standalone window&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same code (HTML+CSS+manifest file and an empty JavaScript file loaded as a service worker) produce good mobile experience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*qDNI5CsWyWWPty5qcM6KaA.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add to home screen is same as installing the app on the&amp;nbsp;device&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the icon is added to the desktop as expected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*u1QOfgyz4iEdl1dZ2zrDPg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and when the icon is clicked, the user gets a nice welcoming screen, colors defined as &lt;code&gt;theme_color&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;background_color&lt;/code&gt; properties in the manifest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*HLOcyRrmJu2AvKN4aqrlCQ.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, in standalone display mode, no URL address bar is visible. Use a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?q=best+mobile-first+CSS+frameworks+today&#34;&gt;good front-end framework&lt;/a&gt; to make the look and feel of your web page as a native app — the user will be delighted!&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-app-nbsp-shell&#34;&gt;The app&amp;nbsp;shell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s mostly conceptual yet important task to think about: in order to deliver good user experience, it&amp;rsquo;s useful to have access to fundamental assets offline in order to react well in case of a network going offline. So, when you build and develop your web site, consider it&amp;rsquo;s a real shell that stays the same and only the contents is changing. This article gives good &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/architecture/app-shell&#34;&gt;concept overview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not something super-new for people who are used to thinking about apps already, or developers of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single-page_application&#34;&gt;SPAs&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s just something to always have in the back of your mind when you look at your own website — what resources are important to deliver to the user even when he&amp;rsquo;s offline? What are the repetitive elements of my web pages? Normally these are the navigation and its surroundings. All these become the &amp;ldquo;shell&amp;rdquo;, being cached on the device for easy access, and the content is dynamically fetched when available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*dEvx7lPNJT-r-tKjqvAXxg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/architecture/app-shell&#34;&gt;Image credits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to implement this strategy for saving resources, one must know how to use the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Cache&#34;&gt;Cache API&lt;/a&gt; through a service worker. The API can also be accessed through the global &lt;code&gt;window&lt;/code&gt; object as well, but working through a SW, we can &amp;ldquo;hook&amp;rdquo; into the events in the worker&amp;rsquo;s life-cycle, i.e. we can validate cache when network connection toggles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;creating-a-service-nbsp-worker&#34;&gt;Creating a service&amp;nbsp;worker&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;gt; Rich offline experiences, periodic background syncs, push notifications — functionality that would normally require a native application — are coming to the web. Service workers provide the technical foundation that all these features rely on. — taken from &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/getting-started/primers/service-workers&#34;&gt;Service Workers: an Introduction&lt;/a&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In basic terms, the service worker is a proxy layer between your stack (HTML+CSS+JS) and the network. The API of service workers boost the functionality of your otherwise normal web pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good starting point could be the sample for &lt;a href=&#34;https://googlechrome.github.io/samples/service-worker/custom-offline-page/index.html&#34;&gt;Service Worker Sample: Custom Offline Page Sample&lt;/a&gt;. If the amount of code seems too much, have a look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/tools/service-worker-libraries/&#34;&gt;tools section&lt;/a&gt; where some libraries are already published to make these functionalities more accessible. For example, if your project uses a task runner, you can implement &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/GoogleChrome/sw-precache#install&#34;&gt;`sw-precache&lt;/a&gt;` (&lt;a href=&#34;https://codelabs.developers.google.com/codelabs/sw-precache/#0&#34;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; is also available&amp;nbsp;;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, personally, it was fun to play a bit with the service worker file, not having access to the DOM directly, but yet having a Web API that should communicate with it was an interesting thing. In the end, I used the example code provided in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/GoogleChrome/sw-precache/tree/master/demo&#34;&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;code&gt;sw-precache&lt;/code&gt; because I&amp;rsquo;m really lazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the exercise, I have this branch for &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kalinchernev/pwa/tree/basics/caching&#34;&gt;the basics of caching the application shell&lt;/a&gt;. What I really like as a side-effect of stealing the gulp file of the demo above is that now I have a basic build system. That helps me in generating a comparatively sophisticated service-worker handling the offline behavior of my web app. Also, it gives me a nicely working &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;gh-pages website&lt;/a&gt; that can be accessed by anyone over HTTPS on &lt;https: kalinchernev.github.io=&#34;&#34; pwa=&#34;&#34;&gt; This makes me really happy, because of several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I already have a self-hosted, manageable (easy to update and deploy), modern web app, that looks like a mobile app. It can be viewed and installed on a mobile device, and later opened in a &amp;ldquo;shell&amp;rdquo;, i.e. not showing broken pages offline mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a task runner like &lt;a href=&#34;http://gulpjs.com/&#34;&gt;gulp&lt;/a&gt; opens a door of opportunities to make my development life even easier than before: I can integrate live reload, include any preprocessing of LESS/SASS, can include babel to turn my ES6 code in ES5 for older browsers, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the &lt;code&gt;sw-precache&lt;/code&gt; even as simple as it is right now, provides me with benefits of easier asset management, as I don&amp;rsquo;t have to go too much into the details of the Cache API if I don&amp;rsquo;t want to, and the mechanism of implementing the worker is easier to update in the future, as I believe the project will be well maintained. So, my task for future maintenance will be to re-generate the worker which is already included on the page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that you already see more opportunities than before. In particular, next time you want to publish information that is important and useful for your users when, say, they travel, consider these options. Imagine you want to provide accessible guides and documentation — just follow the same steps and provide enhanced experience, I&amp;rsquo;m sure it&amp;rsquo;ll pay off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;push-notification&#34;&gt;Push notification&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me briefly indicate some resources that I consider useful for the topic, without going into details, as this feature is going a bit beyond the browser and won&amp;rsquo;t be as beginner-friendly as I&amp;rsquo;d like it to be. This topic deserves another separate article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a start, you can start with &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/web/fundamentals/getting-started/codelabs/push-notifications/&#34;&gt;Adding Push Notifications to a Web App&lt;/a&gt;. It can be well-complemented with &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en/docs/Web/API/Push_API/Using_the_Push_API&#34;&gt;Using the Push API&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/dev-channel/designing-a-web-push-service-3076c0599f3e#.6xi4d77ds&#34;&gt;Designing a Web Push Service&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@paul_kinlan&#34;&gt;Paul Kinlan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from being bright, it will be filled with advancements and further variety in the developers&amp;rsquo; toolbox. Having in mind that browsers have always been an inconsistent environment, it will be vital to keep the following resources at hand and get fresh information every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to underline, that &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@nekrtemplar/progressive-web-apps-aint-google-s-thing-31ca581e7a1#.faazl83yx&#34;&gt;Progressive Web Apps isn&amp;rsquo;t a Google-only thing&lt;/a&gt; although many of the references in this article are going to resources authored by community contributions to Google documentation. This is mainly because the dedication and organization of knowledge seems to the best at the moment. &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.windows.com/msedgedev/2016/07/08/the-progress-of-web-apps/#ZeJAshXJM2BuqDRB.97&#34;&gt;Microsoft are also supporters of PWA&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;http://manifoldjs.com&#34;&gt;manifoldjs&lt;/a&gt; is an interesting project you will probably meet should you decide to make PWA that works as a nice app in Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, Web APIs will surely continue to evolve. You can bookmark the good ol&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://caniuse.com/#search=push&#34;&gt;caniuse.com&lt;/a&gt; to verify whether an API you want to use is supported natively or you&amp;rsquo;ll have to search for a shim/polyfill and similar. Of course, there are many existing libraries and frameworks which are already taking developers attention (causing fatigue&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I speak about experimental features that will change, but I firmly believe that browser vendors are on a good way of collaborating to support native APIs more consistently rapidly in very near future, so these features will be standard before you realize it. Knowing the standards helps you produce more maintainable code and gives you a good idea about the direction of Web, regardless of the popularity and influence of vendor frameworks and libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are simple steps that anyone can take in order to convert their existing websites and web pages in progressive web apps, i.e. pages with HTML+CSS+JavaScript which act like native apps for important functionalities. Installation, caching and push notifications are a growing trend for a reason — they increase user engagement and provide great experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, during the upcoming holidays, have a look at the following Web APIs, and hopefully play with them, provide more value via your web pages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a &lt;code&gt;manifest.json&lt;/code&gt; file describing your app with its assets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;implement caching for the vital assets necessary when offline&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make a simple push notification for events of new content on your pages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, using native Web APIs will be fun during this experimentation, as &lt;a href=&#34;http://kangax.github.io/compat-table/es6/&#34;&gt;Chrome supports a lot of ES6 features&lt;/a&gt; and there is no need for you to transpile your code to see immediate results of your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy and good luck!&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Triage stream-adventure issue queue</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/stream-adventure-triage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/stream-adventure-triage/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;working-on-the-issue-nbsp-queue&#34;&gt;Working on the issue&amp;nbsp;queue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wanted to work on the queue for my own benefit of figuring out what is what, etc. initially, I started working in one way and changed my approach on the way. The goal was simple: organize issues and pull request in an effective way for a maintainer to quickly and easily take yes/no decision on solving a given problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy 1: Prioritize pull requests&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a &amp;ldquo;newbie&amp;rdquo; in both the subject of matter (the streams) and in the project, my first idea was to go through the list of pull requests and categorize them in a way that indicates the readiness to be merged. This way, I imagine, the pull requests being validated and tested can be quickly skimmed and hopefully merged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This strategy didn&amp;rsquo;t work very effective for me, since the process was not linear, i.e. frequently I open 1 pull request which solves 1 issue, and then from this issue, I tend to find related or duplicates, and what if there are other pull requests that solve the same issue in another way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that strategy could be effective if the project has a roadmap or a well-defined list of important bugs/features to be handled in a given sprint or milestone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy 2: Work-out &amp;ldquo;low-hanging fruits&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This strategy seemed a natural reflex for quick gratification after the first strategy didn&amp;rsquo;t work quite well&amp;nbsp;:) The idea is simple: go through issues and find such that are either already solved, duplicates, general questions that are already answered successfully, old issues that are not valid any more, etc. These are quick-wins that give a good feeling similar to the one that you experience when you cross an item from the todo list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that this strategy could be the starting point, rather than a bounce-back reflex as I did. The process of sorting easy or already done issues is a low-barrier entrance into the issue queue. And it naturally leads to the need of reading/searching other related issues which is something that has to be done at any case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy 3: Categorize issues by topic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This small and probably super-obvious step was actually more gratifying than the low-handing fruits. At this stage, I decided that the process of triage the issue queue will be a complementary activity to my own learning path of the module. So, I made a list of the issues, categorized by the topic of the workshopper, i.e. &amp;ldquo;concat&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;http_server&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;http_client&amp;rdquo;, etc. and then sorted them in the same way as I would go through them in the workshopper. This way, I reached a natural flow of working on the problem myself trying to solve it (experiencing the same problems as I&amp;rsquo;d see in the issue queue) and then going through the list of related issues and pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, the sole act of first doing the challenge myself and then reading information and reports about the issue gives a very good background and picture on the way I&amp;rsquo;d approach the issues and the pull requests. Sometimes opening a pull request suggesting an update in the problem definition could be solving many issues coming from misunderstanding the problem or misunderstanding the expected code implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy 4: Prioritize most recent communication&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s an approach of working out issues in open source projects in software or software modules that one does not necessarily use directly everyday or is not affected/blocked at a current time. I didn&amp;rsquo;t prioritize latest communication at this triage because the project is not so big and there aren&amp;rsquo;t so many issues or pull requests. In case the project involves thousand of developers or sub-functionalities that are not easy to see or figure out, but still feels good to contribute back, that strategy could be useful to get into effective flow of solving problems that are important/actual/active at the current moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy 5: Follow your own interest&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar way of strategy 3, which involved prioritizing issues by topic, I could say that it&amp;rsquo;s pretty important to work on issues that are genuinely interesting for oneself. This means that, even if the project was bigger and harder to maintain, the passion which someone has about a topic would always win over a non-interested trivial going through the issue queue solving issues that are not really motivation enough to learn from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;your-feedback-is-nbsp-valuable&#34;&gt;Your feedback is&amp;nbsp;valuable&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarize this meta-article, your feedback on both the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/workshopper/stream-adventure/issues&#34;&gt;repository of the project&lt;/a&gt; and my thoughts are very welcome&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sharing is caring!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a node.js client for the EU Open Data Portal</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/eu-data-portal-nodejs-client/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2016 12:10:11 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/eu-data-portal-nodejs-client/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Planning to make an open data GraphQL server, it was natural to first build a small abstraction wrapper which can be re-used in other projects. Basically, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.npmjs.com/package/odp&#34;&gt;odp library&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about is just a simplified client for fetching data from the EU Open Data Portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-the-library&#34;&gt;Getting the library&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have &lt;a href=&#34;https://nodejs.org/en/&#34;&gt;node.js&lt;/a&gt;, the module can be installed by npm:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;npm install odp
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;library-api&#34;&gt;Library API&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The API of the module is pretty simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;_// Get a range of the whole list of datasets:_


odp.getDatasets({query**:** {limit**:** 100, offset**:** 1}}).then((data) =&amp;amp;gt; {


  console.log(data);


});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, there are 4 methods which match the brief information from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://data.europa.eu/euodp/en/developerscorner&#34;&gt;developers&amp;rsquo; corner&lt;/a&gt;. Methods are: &lt;code&gt;getDatasets&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;getTags&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;getDataset&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;datasetSearch&lt;/code&gt;. It could be that there are more options than that in the API, but these are all I know so far as user of the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kalinchernev/odp/blob/master/README.md#examples&#34;&gt;Examples section&lt;/a&gt; is included in the README file for further details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suggestions and pull requests are welcome at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/kalinchernev/odp&#34;&gt;github page of the project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For inspirations of use, more information about the data or introduction training of the benefits of using open data, visit the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.europeandataportal.eu/&#34;&gt;europeandataportal.eu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debugging node.js in Cloud9 IDE</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/debugging-nodejs-in-cloud9-ide/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/debugging-nodejs-in-cloud9-ide/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In this article I&amp;rsquo;ll be sharing some of my level-up experience learning how to debug node.js apps. It was not easy at first, but once I got it, I felt empowered that now I can work with any code base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debugging is useful for solving vague problems in other people&amp;rsquo;s code and it&amp;rsquo;s also useful for learning how something actually works. The article might be particularly useful for those used to having debugger experience in WebStorm or similar IDEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;quick-reference&#34;&gt;Quick reference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That article is meant to be more like a cheat sheet rather than too detailed step by step guide, here&amp;rsquo;s a go-to list of techniques:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;node-debugger&#34;&gt;Node debugger&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start by the basics — using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://nodejs.org/api/debugger.html&#34;&gt;node&amp;rsquo;s native debugger&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Surnet/swagger-jsdoc/blob/master/example/app.js&#34;&gt;this app&lt;/a&gt; contains a simple server returning a JSON object which is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.be/url?sa=t&amp;amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiG4Pi0qfbOAhUEOhQKHaQICOAQFggcMAA&amp;amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fswagger.io%2Fspecification%2F&amp;amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNH_jZB7rkJVVCg-JHFmeLAHwMnUfw&amp;amp;amp;sig2=R2rG7_9EH1ctFeFwtJ7cPw&amp;amp;amp;bvm=bv.131783435,d.d24&#34;&gt;swagger specification&lt;/a&gt; and I need to debug and see its value. So, in this example, I&amp;rsquo;ll follow this steps to see the contents of the variable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set a break point with &lt;code&gt;debugger&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the script with &lt;code&gt;node debug example/app.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work with the controls of the debugger to reach a good value: &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; to continue and &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; for next&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;repl&lt;/code&gt; to execute some code which access current state of the system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*CHRmYU912yZDRmqz7Z490w.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;simple-script&#34;&gt;Simple script&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a break point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press the Run button to execute the default node runner (ensure the debugger is enabled — &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/debugging-your-code&#34;&gt;more info&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*I-mVNLptBFDG-EaJpLR6rQ.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mocha-tests&#34;&gt;Mocha tests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/experimental-features&#34;&gt;experimental feature&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*-8oDjYBTEU4-G8H5_vw5lg.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable &amp;lsquo;Tests&amp;rdquo; from the editor settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Refresh the page and see the panel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put a break point in the test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable debugging in the &amp;ldquo;Test&amp;rdquo; panel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the test suite or scenario&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feature actually worked for me, I felt just the same way when I made my first &lt;a href=&#34;http://mortalkombat.wikia.com/wiki/Animality&#34;&gt;animality in MK3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*OHINaf_jcvN75EN1M0ozlQ.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;command-line-apps&#34;&gt;Command-line apps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact it&amp;rsquo;s almost identical to debugging a simple script, the only detail you have to notice is an input box where you put the actual command as if ran in the command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the command-line app and place a break point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the Run menu to start the process in debug more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change the input process name and restart the runner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*V9xHSnqzwCasqzHiHyBD5Q.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;feedback-is-nbsp-welcome&#34;&gt;Feedback is&amp;nbsp;welcome&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the comments below to share your techniques and opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>