<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cloud on Kalin Chernev</title>
    <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/tags/cloud/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cloud on Kalin Chernev</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - 2017</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://kalinchernev.github.io/tags/cloud/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>January Digest 2017</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/january-digest-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/january-digest-2017/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I’ve prepared a warm-up digest for those of you who made a resolution to improve their JavaScript skills in 2017, so let’s get it started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stories&#34;&gt;Stories&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I published 2 articles this month and I enjoyed writing both of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kalin.chernev/problem-first-problem-solving-87369b84551f#.zg5l97itd&#34;&gt;Problem-first problem-solving&lt;/a&gt; — don’t be mislead by the title, it’s about positive concepts going randomly through my brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://restful.io/agile-documentation-for-your-api-driven-project-based-on-open-api-standards-11e54d4326bb#.jaw6kcohk&#34;&gt;Agile documentation for your API-driven project&lt;/a&gt; — this got a tweet from the community few minutes after being published. So, the spread started before I make a tweet about the new publication myself. Nothing makes me happier than that as a writer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got enthusiastic to write this article after release 1.9.0 of &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Surnet/swagger-jsdoc&#34;&gt;swagger-jsdoc&lt;/a&gt; which introduced 2 new features. Both of them being focused on developers’ experience and productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;javascript&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s just the beginning of 2017, so let’s warm up right for it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nodesource.com/blog/the-21-most-awesome-awesome-lists-for-node-js-developers&#34;&gt;The 21 Most Awesome Awesome Lists for Node.js Developers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://risingstars2016.js.org/&#34;&gt;2016 rising stars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.mybridge.co/node-js-top-10-articles-of-the-year-v-2017-79df8269d0f3#.naz5q020y&#34;&gt;Node.JS Top 10 Articles of the Year (v.2017)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.risingstack.com/node-js-async-best-practices-avoiding-callback-hell-node-js-at-scale/&#34;&gt;Node.js Async Best Practices &amp;amp; Avoiding Callback Hell — Node.js at Scale&lt;/a&gt; — this article is full of advertisements just as a typical American TV show. It’s also as good as such because it shows you problems and solutions that you might actually have in your real life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one more which is not only about JavaScript but the broader spectrum of front-end development: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gitbook.com/book/frontendmasters/front-end-handbook-2017/details&#34;&gt;Front-End Developer Handbook 2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cloud&#34;&gt;Cloud&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that video gives a useful overview of one of the new hypes: serverless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Dh_UXXtSvjQ?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, this feels down-to-earth about production usage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/c4rvh_Iq6LE?rel=0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my personal opinion, this “serverless” hype is not a ground-breaking new technology, but a smooth transition towards customer-oriented architectures and services. Containers could be considered as a ground-breaking thing which solve problems in infrastructure management, and they will probably be still the background “hidden” behind serverless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I visualize a transition towards customer-oriented API architectures and services, I imagine services like &lt;a href=&#34;http://swagger.io/go-serverless-with-swaggerhub-and-amazon/&#34;&gt;SwaggerHub&lt;/a&gt; which hide complexity of infrastructure management and let’s the user focus on building products.&lt;/span&gt; I also imagine that at some point Amazon will be in a position to offer amazing user AND developers experience directly in the cloud when &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/janakirammsv/2016/07/18/the-master-plan-behind-amazons-acquisition-of-cloud9-ide/#6e580c0028db&#34;&gt;Cloud9 comes move integrated&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, AWS (? will ?) be the de-facto platform for building cloud applications where the user starts off easily — just clicking here and there and making configurations which integrate what-ever is necessary, where-ever necessary. And when super-specific tweak is necessary, code editor with all &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kalin.chernev/debugging-node-js-in-cloud9-ide-59712c043fb2&#34;&gt;debugging capabilities&lt;/a&gt; will be at hand. Thus, covering scenarios from small startup projects that don’t want to focus on infrastructure, to enterprise which is there because of the fine control over the server side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;trends&#34;&gt;Trends&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a similar note about trends, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oracle.com/corporate/acquisitions/apiary/index.html&#34;&gt;Apiary got acquired by Oracle&lt;/a&gt;. Though I’m not a pro at understanding mergers, it’s obvious that API economy companies are on success reaping wave. Only few months ago &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/greatspeculations/2016/09/13/heres-why-google-is-acquiring-apigee/#52eceafc693f&#34;&gt;Apigee was in the news in a similar way&lt;/a&gt;, and there is a compelling reason for these trending acquisitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;time-saving-tricks&#34;&gt;Time-saving tricks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;phpstorm-convert-between-array-syntax&#34;&gt;PHPStorm convert between array syntax&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laugh at me, but I still sometimes see &lt;code&gt;array()&lt;/code&gt; syntax during my work (and not &lt;code&gt;[]&lt;/code&gt;) It appeared to be an easy thing to change automatically in the editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Code | Inspect Code...&lt;/code&gt; — run it on your files. One of the inspections called &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Traditional syntax array literal detected&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alternatively just run that specific inspection only via &lt;code&gt;Code | Run Inspection by Name...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once done, you will see a list with results. Find that particular inspection in results (in case if 1st option was used (all inspections)).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From there you can apply “Fix it” action on all (or individual) results of that inspection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*t5kfn0iW_I3uC3mWxA5Ntg.png&#34; alt=&#34;php storm converting array syntax&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Checking the daily ebook by&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.packtpub.com/packt/offers/free-learning&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Packt’s Free Leaning campaign&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an option to subscribe for updates via twitter or facebook, which is understandable. This is a good way to have leads and metrics of the campaign. However, it’s not very practical to open the website and see it every day, thus I made a lazy-logic implementation to be able to check this from the command line like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ node ~/scripts/freeEbook.js
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s the gist for it (it’s super-lazy)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;https://gist.github.com/kalinchernev/5f67405d46914897ee8ff95b46b55898.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This script is just the basic concept that can be integrated with internal cron tasks or cloud services to automate the check. For example, I imagine that with some investigation it will be possible to work out an &lt;a href=&#34;https://auth0.com/blog/if-this-then-node-dot-js-extending-ifttt-with-webtask-dot-io/&#34;&gt;integration with IFTTT&lt;/a&gt; or a similar service.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud9 IDE</title>
      <link>https://kalinchernev.github.io/cloud9-editor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://kalinchernev.github.io/cloud9-editor/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*uc-REJYHbk02nuzVQmDHHQ.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few months ago I attended a &lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@kalin.chernev/coding-battle-at-microsoft-innovation-center-brussels-the-rise-of-the-bots-f0887c15e257&#34;&gt;coding competition&lt;/a&gt;. In the end of the event the winners demonstrated one of their tools: the &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io&#34;&gt;Cloud9 editor&lt;/a&gt;. Then it hit me — I had to experiment with it! Later I used it working on various projects in my free time. Here I&amp;rsquo;m going to share my experience so far — I&amp;rsquo;m a happy user&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cloud9-is-nbsp-great&#34;&gt;Cloud9 is&amp;nbsp;great&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I&amp;rsquo;ve found several key points/facts why I consider the editor to be truly astounding tool:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility and User/Developer experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pair_programming&#34;&gt;Pair programming&lt;/a&gt; and education&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaboration and open source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accessibility&#34;&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool is currently &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/pricing&#34;&gt;free&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/c9&#34;&gt;open source&lt;/a&gt;. Even if you&amp;rsquo;re not a technical person you already have reason #1 to either make a &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/signup&#34;&gt;new registration&lt;/a&gt; or use your existing code-oriented account to &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/login&#34;&gt;log in&lt;/a&gt; to the service. (No affiliation in the links) If you are non-technical, but very business person, you might know that &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/blog/great-news/&#34;&gt;Amazon will probably grow Cloud9 in the future&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you are a technical person and you take a closer look, you&amp;rsquo;ll see that it&amp;rsquo;s a charming service of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ace.c9.io/#nav=about&#34;&gt;ace&lt;/a&gt; which directly accesses &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.docker.com/&#34;&gt;docker&lt;/a&gt; instances. The first time I showed a working &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/create-a-workspace&#34;&gt;workspace&lt;/a&gt; to a friend developer telling him to use the environment just as Ubuntu — the response was something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*DBGdHlkB6DVjBy62d3TANQ.gif&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, he setup all his bash aliases and specific configurations and started to work with the terminal just as he&amp;rsquo;s working with his own Linux machine&amp;nbsp;:)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pair-programming-and-education&#34;&gt;Pair programming and education&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as the environment was ready (understand having all the aliases and custom shell scripts, drush, drupal console, etc. cli tools) we went into using some of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/share-a-workspace#section-collaboration-features&#34;&gt;collaboration features&lt;/a&gt;. I will not put a meme here, but I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you this: the experience is very similar to using Google Drive for collaborating on documents in real-time, so if you like this — you&amp;rsquo;ll surely like this real-time coding experience too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pair_programming&#34;&gt;Pair programming&lt;/a&gt; on same git branch and code base is not something we usually do for various reasons, but if you like doing it, or you need to do it — I&amp;rsquo;d definitely recommend you Cloud9. You can pair program remotely just as you&amp;rsquo;d normally do on 1 computer: sharing terminal, files, git branches, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From these pair program opportunities come also very interesting education opportunities. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs50.harvard.edu/&#34;&gt;CS50&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.freecodecamp.com/challenges/start-a-nodejs-server&#34;&gt;freeCodeCamp&lt;/a&gt;. These are good case studies of the cloud editor to encourage people of all walks of life to give programming a try and learn their &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/supported-languages&#34;&gt;preferred programming language&lt;/a&gt; without any special computer hardware requirements, i.e. they can code real applications in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaboration-and-open-nbsp-source&#34;&gt;Collaboration and open&amp;nbsp;source&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the service is free and very fun to use, it&amp;rsquo;s naturally an optional tool when working on various projects requiring tight collaboration such as open source projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I decided to work on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Surnet/swagger-jsdoc&#34;&gt;swagger-jsdoc&lt;/a&gt; node module which I used for a small project. All I had to do to make a pull request is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a new workspace (new virtual machine in the cloud)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Git clone the fork repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new branch and do your task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push back to fork repository and open a pull request&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I didn&amp;rsquo;t even have to install any software, all I had to make this contribution was to open my browser and use Cloud9 as a cloud service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;keybindings&#34;&gt;Keybindings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the items I&amp;rsquo;m using quite often and sometimes get a WOW effect from people watching me doing things like that in my browser:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/multiple-cursors&#34;&gt;Multiple cursors&lt;/a&gt; (yep, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sublimetext.com/&#34;&gt;sublime&lt;/a&gt; is to blame for our expectations)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Command line tricks work just well (Ctrl+U, Ctrl+L)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/keybindings&#34;&gt;Find in tree&lt;/a&gt; (and others)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.c9.io/docs/find-and-replacing-in-files#find-in-files&#34;&gt;Search/Find&lt;/a&gt; is handy working with namespaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think normally people don&amp;rsquo;t expect a full IDE experience in the browser, as I didn&amp;rsquo;t too, and that&amp;rsquo;s the reason I mentioned Docked previously for an eye-opener. Just by the way, PHP developers might be even more surprised with things like &lt;a href=&#34;https://c9.io/blog/debug-your-php-code-with-xdebug-and-cloud9/&#34;&gt;xdebugger&lt;/a&gt; being available in their development environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;setting-up-drupal-nbsp-8&#34;&gt;Setting up Drupal&amp;nbsp;8&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might come even more shocking for people having an idea what &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.drupal.org/&#34;&gt;Drupal&lt;/a&gt; is. It&amp;rsquo;s an association of heavy CMS with high resource demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, do the following the sake of having your WOW moment yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new workspace based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/drupal-composer/drupal-project&#34;&gt;Drupal Composer&lt;/a&gt; github repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the instructions to run an installation from the cli or the web (you might need to read &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.c9.io/t/setting-up-mysql/1718&#34;&gt;this MySQL&lt;/a&gt; article if you don&amp;rsquo;t have the idea to see your &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.ubuntu.com/community/EnvironmentVariables&#34;&gt;environment variables&lt;/a&gt; from the command line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Profit from having a running Drupal 8 which uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://getcomposer.org/&#34;&gt;Composer&lt;/a&gt; scripts for managing modules and dependencies to external libraries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*12EXDc2rgRcy11wQk4SVjA.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>